Srinivas Rao Potlapally

Java Full stack developer

+1(901) 232-1448 | Srinivasraop03@gmail.com | LinkedIn: in/srinivas-rao-potlapally

SUMMARY

Java Full Stack Developer with around 4+ years of experience in designing, developing, and deploying full-stack web applications. Proficient in Java, JavaScript, HTML/CSS, and frameworks and libraries. Experience in front-end and back-end development, database management, and version control. Proficient in Java frameworks such as Spring MVC, Hibernate, and Spring Boot, with experience in creating Microservices architectures, resulting in a 30% improvement in system scalability and a 20% reduction in deployment times.

SKILLS

Methodology: SDLC, Agile, Waterfall Languages: C, C++, Java, Python

Frameworks: Spring MVC, Hibernate, Node.js, React.js, Restful API, SOAP, WebSocket, RabbitMQ, SaaS, Tailwind,

Next.js, Express.js, Angular.js

Web Technologies: HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, XML, YAML,

JSON, Ajax, jQuery, Redux, TypeScript, JavaScript

IDEs: PyCharm, Jupyter Notebook, Visual Studio Code Cloud Technology: Azure, AWS, Docker, Kubernetes Application Server: Apache Tomcat, WebSphere

Databases: SQL, MySQL, MongoDB, SQL Server, PostgreSQL Version Control/ Other Tools: Git, Postman, CI/CD, Jenkins,

Jira, Webpack, Rally, Junit, Atom

Operating Systems: Linux, Windows, Mac

EDUCATION

Masters in Information Systems, University of Memphis, Memphis, TN Bachelors in Civil Engineering,

VBIT, Hyderabad, India

January 2023 – December 2024

June 2016 - September 2020

EXPERIENCE

Java Full Stack Developer | Freddie Mac, USA | January 2024 – Present

- Facilitated all phases of the Software development life cycle (SDLC) using Agile Methodology.
- Developed front-end components using React JS and integrated components with backend services to create seamless user experiences.
- Implemented authentication and authorization using Spring Security to secure web applications, reducing security vulnerabilities by 30% and enhancing user data protection.
- Integrated PostgreSQL for data storage and retrieval, implementing database migrations and transactions, resulting in a 25% improvement in data retrieval speed and efficiency.
- Leveraged AWS Services such as EC2, S3, RDS, and Lambda for deploying, scaling, and managing cloud-based applications, leading to a 40% reduction in infrastructure costs and a 30% improvement in application scalability and performance.
- Spearheaded a development project, enhancing testing protocols and code quality in the SDLC, resulting in a 20% drop in bug reports.

Full Stack Developer | Streebo Inc, India | September 2020 - December 2023

- Experience in using Agile methodology and participated in Scrum meetings, sprint planning and used JIRA as a tracking tool for sprints.
- Built robust server-side applications interacting with databases employing Spring Boot and Hibernate, directly leading to a 15% decrease in data retrieval times.
- Configured Hibernate configuration files to persist data to the MongoDB database, reducing data processing time by 25% and improving database query efficiency by 20%.
- Hands-on practice of using GIT for version control, Maven for building scripts, and configured log4j.
- Experience in using Jenkins in code deployment and migrating stored procedures from SQL to MySQL, resulting in a 30% reduction in time for deployment and a 20% improvement in database performance.
- Expertise in deploying applications on Amazon Web Service (AWS), such as building, testing, and deploying Identity Microservices, leading to a 25% increase in the scalability and reliability of applications.
- Experience in integrating Ansible into CI/CD pipelines to automate the build, test, and deployment processes, reducing manual intervention and improving overall efficiency.
- Incorporated Model-View-Controller (MVC) pattern to implement microservices for user authentication RESTful API's. With the help of Spring Boot, accelerated the development of API's upon joining the team.
- Integrated layers to enhance application flexibility using Spring Framework, achieving a 25% boost in code maintainability and faster development cycles, lowering maintenance costs.
- Led the planning of projects and coordinated web-based project management tasks with HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and Reactoptimized website performance, resulting in an increase in user retention and a rise in conversion rates.